<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Canada | Near Improv]]></title>
  <link href="http://alpha-beta-soup.github.io/blog/categories/canada/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alpha-beta-soup.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-13T18:45:49+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://alpha-beta-soup.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Richard Law]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One Day in Montréal]]></title>
    <link href="http://alpha-beta-soup.github.io/blog/2014/06/12/montreal-transit/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-12T17:58:10+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://alpha-beta-soup.github.io/blog/2014/06/12/montreal-transit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This video of Montréal&rsquo;s transit system fell across my path today, made by Colin
Stewart and Ahmed El-Geneidy at McGill University&rsquo;s School of Urban Planning. I&rsquo;ve
been reading a bit of professor El-Geneidy&rsquo;s work recently for my own research, and
I&rsquo;ve recently been entertaining the idea of visiting Montréal for an extended period
of time once I print a thesis onto a reconstituted tree. Providence?</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/1ztMm5xmk3M" allowfullscreen></iframe></div></p>

<p>The video shows 24 hours of transit, from 4:30 in the morning for the Société de
transport de Montréal (STM), drilling down to individual scheduled trips. It distinguishes
between the green, orange, yellow and blue metro lines as well as buses operating every ten minutes
(the purple points) and &ldquo;regular&rdquo; buses (white).</p>

<p>It is presented on quite a high-resolution basemap, with plenty of attendant information.</p>

<p>While it is an interesting look at the network operation, there are a handful of
problems I have with this video that anyone reading may like to think about if
they are to make their own animation.</p>

<p>Note: if you&rsquo;re content with just looking at the cool flashing lights (and it is cool!)
don&rsquo;t bother reading on. I&rsquo;m going to focus on the negatives and leave the positives
as self-evident. Oh, I&rsquo;m such an optimistic young fellow.</p>

<hr />

<h2>Critique</h2>

<hr />

<p>Firstly, the information given in the video margins is a little overbearing, and
isn&rsquo;t even what I would consider to be the most important information. We are not
told what day of the week is represented (weekday schedules are typically different
from Saturday and Sunday schedules), or where the data is from. Even in the video
description, we have no link to further information. It almost seems as though
it is a recruitment device for transit buffs to hit McGill&rsquo;s website. Which worked
for me, let it be known, but I&rsquo;d still like some more information on how this was
constructed&mdash;especially if it is made with open data.</p>

<p>The margin of the video could be improved if the unnecessary information was removed
entirely (and left to text descriptions or the embedding web page) or allowed to fade
out after the first 20 or so seconds. Ideally, only time would remain after this
introductory period.</p>

<p>The base map, although nice in isolation, is too distracting. The blue
&lsquo;pops&rsquo; when it is the least important piece of information on the map. The St. Lawrence
River can be used here to give context to the map, but even in this capacity the basemap
works against intuition by orienting the map away from north. As a foreigner, I am
only vaguely aware of the shape of Montréal, but I still would have recognised it
immediately if north was up as per convention. In short, the colours and orientation
of the basemap ensure the basemap fails at its primary goal of providing immediate
contextual recognition.</p>

<p>Both colour and size are used to distinguish the types of modes represented, which
is appropriate. For the metro lines, the yellow and orange are hard to distinguish
on moving objects that (seem?) to share a line, although the use of a track is good.
I don&rsquo;t know if the capacity of a vehicle on the metro is several orders of magnitude
greater than a bus, but it probably is, and the relative size of the metro to the buses
is appropriate. However I think the metro points are probably a little too big, as they
bleed into each other and obscure the bus routes.</p>

<p>I think the two types of bus should have points of the same size (unless one has
a greater per-vehicle capacity), and allow small traces for the vehicles to distinguish
the higher frequency in one, which should emerge naturally if they are indeed high-frequency.</p>

<p>It is also worth asking whether the format is appropriate. Is a video a useful format
for presenting this information? The people in the comments seem happy enough, with
only one or two pointing out that this shows an idealised system where nothing comes
early or late&hellip; or arrives with no seats left. Could an interactive data visualisation
show the same information with additional value? I think so; particularly in that
I&rsquo;d like to zoom into particular neighbourhoods. I do appreciate, however, that
the authors of the video probably did this in their free time, and a video has higher
bang for your buck.</p>

<p>The other in-your-face issue with video as a format is that you&rsquo;re stuck with the
frame rate the authors found most interesting&hellip; or bearable given the number of times
they must have seen this in preparing it. I&rsquo;d love to slow it down during the busiest
moments, but alas.</p>

<p>The music. No comment. Mute it. Yuck.</p>

<hr />

<h2>Summary</h2>

<hr />

<p>Overall, this is an effective and interesting visualisation, but one that needs
a tidy-up around the edges&mdash;literally and figuratively.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
